<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="nicola12117633.css"?>

<document xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> 
	<heading1>
		Using Images on Your Blog!
	</heading1>
	<heading2>
		A Guide to Attribution for Irish Bloggers
	</heading2>
	<heading3>
		By Nicola O'Sullivan 
	</heading3>
	<heading4>
		10th March 2017
	</heading4>
<image1> 
	<html:img src="header.jpg" alt="banner" style="width:100%;"></html:img>
</image1>
<topic>
	Introduction
</topic>
<paragraph> 
	Images can greatly enhance your blog posts. They draw readers in, and can help support your writing. These images may be screenshots, or photos, that you have taken yourself. 
</paragraph>
<paragraph>
	However, if you have taken the images from the internet, you need to follow copyright law. Using images per the law will give your blog more credibility with your readers. Transparency is important for building trust with your readers, and refencing your sources creates a transparent environment <citation>(Kuhn, 2007)</citation>. 
</paragraph>
<topic>
Understanding Copyright Law in Ireland 
</topic>
<paragraph>
In Ireland, the law that governs online images is set out by the Copyright and Related Acts 2000 <citation>(Irishstatutebook.ie, 2000)</citation>. 
</paragraph>
<paragraph>
The following are covered under this Act: 
</paragraph>
<paragraph> 
<bullet>
	“original literary, dramatic, musical and artistic works
</bullet>
<bullet>
	film, sound recordings, broadcasts and the typographical arrangement of published editions
</bullet>
<bullet>
	computer software and non-original databases performances” <citation>(Ivaro.ie, 2017)</citation>
</bullet>
</paragraph>
<paragraph>
Online images are protected under this act. As soon as an image is made, the creator owns the copyright. Copyright restrictions remain in place until 70 years after the artist’s death. However, rights may be transferred or borrowed through licensing. 
</paragraph>
<topic>
Purchasing Image Rights
</topic>
<paragraph>
	If you need to obtain professional quality images, you can license stock photos. Some licenses allow you to use the image once only. Royalty-free images, however, can be used as often as you like, once you purchase the original license <citation>(Techopedia, 2017)</citation>. It is important to read the fine print when purchasing image rights, as all websites will have different terms. 
</paragraph>
<paragraph>
Here are some commonly used stock photo websites:
</paragraph>
<paragraph>
<bullet>
	 <html:a href="https://stock.adobe.com/ie/" target="_blank">Adobe Stock</html:a> 
</bullet>
<bullet>
<html:a href="http://www.gettyimages.ie/" target="_blank">Getty Images</html:a> 
</bullet>
<bullet>
<html:a href="https://www.shutterstock.com/" target="_blank">Shutterstock</html:a> 
</bullet>
</paragraph>
<topic>
Obtaining Free images
</topic>
<paragraph>
Alternatively, you can obtain images that have been made freely available. These images are made free through Creative Commons Zero (CC0). The owners of the images have waived their rights and allowed their work to enter the public domain <citation>(Creative Commons, 2017)</citation>. You will have a more limited selection to choose from than with stock photos. However, there are many good quality images available free of charge. 
</paragraph>
<paragraph>
Some of the images may still come with conditions (e.g. ‘attribution required’), therefore you should carefully read the terms of each individual image you acquire. 
</paragraph>
<paragraph>
Here are some commonly used websites offering free images:
</paragraph>
<paragraph>
<bullet>
<html:a href="https://pixabay.com/" target="_blank">Pixabay</html:a> 
</bullet>
<bullet>
<html:a href="https://www.pexels.com/ " target="_blank">Pexels</html:a> 
</bullet>
</paragraph>
<topic>
Attributing images 
</topic>
<paragraph>
While some images can be used without attribution, some terms will state that you must give the source. It is good blogging etiquette to give the source of any media you use in your posts. The ideal attribution gives the title, author, source and license <citation>(Creative Commons Wiki, 2017)</citation>. You can also include any changes you have made to the photo.
</paragraph>
<topic>
	References 
</topic>
<reference>
<author>Creative Commons.</author> <year>(2017)</year>. CC0 - Creative Commons. [online] Available at:
 	https://creativecommons.org/share-your-work/public-
 	<paragraph>domain/cc0/ [Accessed 8 Mar. 
 	2017] </paragraph>
 </reference>
 <reference>
 <author>Creative Commons Wiki.</author><year>(2017)</year>. Best practices for attribution - Creative Commons. [online]
 	 Available at: 
 	<paragraph> https://wiki.creativecommons.org/wiki/Best_practices_for_attribution 
 	[Accessed 8 Mar. 2017] </paragraph>
 </reference>
 <reference>
<author>Irishstatutebook.ie. </author><year>(2000)</year>. Copyright and Related Rights Act, 2000. [online] Available 
 	at: 
 	<paragraph>http://www.irishstatutebook.ie/eli/2000/act/28/enacted/en/html [Accessed 8 
 	Mar 2017] </paragraph>
 </reference>
 <reference>
<author>Ivaro.ie. </author><year>(2017)</year>. Copyright – Irish Visual Rights Association. [online] Available at: 
 	http://ivaro.ie/copyright/ [Accessed 8 Mar. 2017] 
 </reference>
<reference>
<author>Kuhn, M.</author> <year>(2007)</year>. Interactivity and Prioritizing the Human: A Code of Blogging Ethics. 
	<paragraph>
 	Journal of Mass Media Ethics, 22(1) [online] [accessed 8 Mar 2017]  
 </paragraph>
</reference>
<reference>
<author> Techopedia </author><year>(2017)</year>. What is a Stock Photo? - Definition from Techopedia. [online] Available at: https://
	<paragraph>www.techopedia.com/definition/2047/stock-photo [Accessed 8 Mar. 2017].</paragraph>
</reference>

 <date>
 Last Edited 10 March 2017 by <editor>Nicola O'Sullivan</editor> 
</date>
</document>